Guide to the Miller-Auchincloss Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Miller-Auchincloss papers
1917-1918
MS 825
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(6 boxes)
Correspondence and memoranda related to the work of David Miller and Gordon Auchincloss (who were law partners) as special representatives of the State Department. Their task was to gather information about commercial and financial activities based in the United States that might benefit Germany and her allies.
Miller, David Hunter, 1875-1961
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Miller & Auchincloss Papers consist of two linear feet of correspondence and memoranda related to the work of law partners David Hunter Miller (1875-1954) and Gordon Auchincloss (1886-1943) as special representatives of the State Department in New York City between March 1917 and August 1918. The appointment went first to Auchincloss, but Miller took over the position shortly after 24 May 1917, when Auchincloss became assistant to the Counselor in the State Department. Miller served in various diplomatic capacities in Paris and London between October 1918 and June 1919, and then continued as representative of the State Department until he resigned the following October.
The duty of the special representative was to gather information at government request about activities with roots in the United States that might be intended to benefit Germany and her allies. Most of the inquiries had to do with transactions between American banks and those in neutral countries in Europe and South America on behalf of their respective clients. These transactions came to the attention of the government mainly through censorship of cables. There were also inquiries about shipments to neutral countries, enemy aliens in the United States, and representatives of American businesses abroad. The government officials with whom Auchincloss and Miller most often corresponded mere Leland Harrison (State Department), Frank E. Carstarphen (Office of the U.S. Attorney for the Southern District of New York), Arthur Woods (New York City Police Commissioner), Dudley Field Malone (Collector of the Port of New York), A.B. Hoff (Naval Communication Service, Office of the Cable Censor), and William J. Flynn (Secret Service). Most of the other correspondents were lawyers or officers of banks and businesses.
The diaries of Auchincloss (1917 Mar-May) and Miller (1917 May-Jun) as special representatives of the State Department are part of the Gordon Auchincloss Papers, Manuscript Group No. 580.
Biographical / Historical
David Hunter Miller (1875-1954): lawyer; admitted to New York Bar, 1911; special assistant in the State Department, 1917; served on the Inquiry under Col. House, 1917-1918, and at the Peace Conference, 1919; active in League of Nations; editor of the Treaties, State Department, 1929; author of numerous books on history, international law, etc.
Business; Law; Trading with the enemy; World War, 1914-1918; United States -- Foreign relations; Lawyers; Auchincloss, Gordon, 1886-1943; Carstarphen, Frank E. (Frank Ellice), 1871-1952; Flynn, William J., 1924-; Harrison, Leland, 1883-1951; Hoff, A. B.; Malone, Dudley Field; Miller, David Hunter, 1875-1961; Polk, Frank Lyon, 1871-1943; Wiseman, William, Sir, 1885-; Woods, Arthur, 1870-1942; United States. Department of State
- Inventory, 1917-1918; 2.25 linear feet (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The arrangement is alphabetical. Most papers are filed under the name of a person or company under investigation, but since most matters involved several parties, the choice of file headings was necessarily somewhat arbitrary. Papers about banking transactions are usually filed under the name of the American bank that attempted to cable the transfer, and papers about German-connected businesses are filed under the name of the firm or one of its representatives. Correspondence is usually filed under the name of the correspondent (usually a government. official) only when it is not related to any particular investigation, but Leland Harrison is an important exception to this generalization. There are also a few topical files: "Gold exports," "Mexico," "South America," "Trading with the enemy."
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Exchange National Bank (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Express Company (1917 Jun-Jul) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Express Company (1917 Aug-Sep) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Metal Company (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Smelting and Refining Company (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Auchincloss, Gordon (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Becker Steel Company of America (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bell, Gordon Knox (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Boissevain and Co. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Browne, Edward B.M. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - C (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Carstarphen, Frank E. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chapeaurouge, Alfred de (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Crampton, Henry E. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Culbertson, William S. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - D (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - E (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Equitable Trust Company of New York
    - 1917 March - July 14, July 16 - August 18, August 20 - November (Box 1, Folder 19-22)
  - F (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Farmer's Loan and Trust Company (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fearon Brown Company (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Flynn, William J. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - France and Canada Steamship Company (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - G (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - General Electric Company (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - German banks in South America and Mexico, referred messages to and from (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Gold exports (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Goldman, Sachs and Co. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Guaranty Trust Company of New York
    - 1917 January-October (Box 2, Folder 32-37)
  - H (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Hamburg American Line (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Hanover National Bank of the City of New York (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Harrison, Leland
    - 1917 April - August 27, 1917 September - 1918 June (Box 3, Folder 41-44)
  - Helmolt, Charles von (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Horst, George D. (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Hülfsaktion für Deutsche and Osterr.-Ungar. (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Gefangene in Siberien, Tientsin (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - I (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Irving National Bank (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Iselin (A.) and Co. (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Isthmian Pacific Railway Company (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - J (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - K (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Knauth, Nachod and Kuhne (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Kuhn, Loeb and Co.: holdings of property for German account (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - L (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Ladenburg, Thalmann and Co. (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Lippmann, Rosenthal and Co. (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - M (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Malone, Dudley Field (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Marshall, H. Snowden (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Merchants' Loan and Trust Company (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Mexico (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Miller, David Hunter: memorandum and covering letter re: supervision of payments to neutral countries (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Müller, Schall and Co.
    - 1917 April-November (Box 4, Folder 65-66)
  - N (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - National Bank of Commerce in New York
    - 1917 June - September 12, September 15 - October (Box 4, Folder 68-69)
  - National City Bank
    - 1917 March-December (Box 4, Folder 70-72)
  - National Park Bank of New York (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Naval Communication Service, Office of the Cable Censor:
    - correspondence (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - memorandum re: press associations, newspapers, and correspondents (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Neutral countries, merchandise held for: circular inquiries (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Neutral countries, remittances to (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - O-P (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Paige, Eva C. (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Phillips, William (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Polk, Frank Lyon (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Q (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - R (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Sa - Sm (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Sp - Sz (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Schmidt, Hugo (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Schroeder, Hans (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Schultz and Ruckgaber (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Solvay Process Company (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - South America (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Sveriges Privata Centralbank (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - T (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Trading with the enemy:
    - inquiries (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - replies (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Trone, S. A. (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - U-V (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - W (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Wätjen, Toel and Company (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Winslow, Lanier (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Wiseman, William (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Woods, Arthur (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Y - Z (Box 6, Folder 100)